International Rescue Committee, Central America Records 1999.0109
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
International Rescue Committee, Central America Records
1976-2000
1999.0109
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
40.0 Linear feet
The collection is comprised of materials documenting the immigration of Latin Americans, in to the United States, during the 1980s and 1990s, and the International Rescue Committee's role in assiting that immigration. The collection consists of administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, notes, photographs, and transcripts.
History
The International Rescue Committee (IRC) was founded in 1933 as a responce to Adolf Hitler's rise to power in Germany. Responding to a plea by Albert Einstein, a group of 51 Americans organized themselves as the International Relief Association in order to help protect anti-Nazi leaders from Hitler's Gestapo. In 1940 the group expanded as refugees from across Europe fled Nazi occupied areas, and following World War II the International Rescue Committee was officially formed, expanding the organization's reach across the world.
The IRC continued to assist refugees and emigrants following the war, as turbulent events across Europe forced thousands to flee. During the Hungarian Revolution of 1956 the IRC was active in assisting the thousands of refugees that fled the country, providing money, housing, medical care, and other forms of relief. During the cold war the IRC was committed to the resettlement of refugees in the United States, and helped settle refugees from across the world. During the Vietnam War the IRC helped many of the Vietnamese people displaced by the war, establishing orphanages, medical clinics, schools, and rehabilitation centers. The IRC also assisted refugees of the Khmer Rouge in Cambodia during the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s.
In addition to helping refugees from Europe, Asia, and Africa, the IRC has also played an important role in assiting refugees from Latin America. Beginning with Fidel Castro's rise to power in 1959 and continuing throughout the 20th century, the IRC has assisted in the resettlement of numerous exiles from Central and South America.
The achievements of IRC, carried out primarily by its volunteers, have led the nation's leading business publications to cite it as one of America's best managed and effective voluntary agencies. Its members have received numerous awards for their work with the agency, as the organization has helped millions of people escape war, poverty, and the tumult of changing governments. The IRC continues to operate today by responding to the world’s worst humanitarian crises, and providing an environment for people to survive and rebuild their lives.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the collection is comprised of materials documenting the immigration of Latin Americans in to the United States during the 1980s and 1990s. Consisting of administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, notes, photographs (facsimiles), and transcripts (translations), the collection documents the work done by the New Jersey office of the International Rescue Committee. Subjects in the collection include Career Center, Inc., the United States Department of Justice, World Education Services, Inc., and Legal Immigration and Employment for Internationals into the United States. Materials in the collection consist of documents related to immigrants from countries throughout the world, including Ecuador, Puerto Rico, Peru, Mexico, Santo Domingo, Colombia, the Dominican Republic, Argentina, Guatemala, Mexico, Panama, and Ethiopia.
Access
The collection is open and available for research with the completion of a required confidentiality affidavit. The Access Policy is also available.
Provenance and Acquisition
The records were donated in 1999 by the New Jersey Office of the International Rescue Committee (IRC).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to [children's literature and associated artwork, nursing education and leadership, literature, various aspects of Connecticut history, the experiences of Connecticut residents while in the military, alternative lifestyles, politics and publications, public polling and survey research [See especially the Papers of James Vicary, Samuel Lubell, Paul K. Perry, Warren Mitofsky, Daniel Yankelovich, and Archibald Crossley], Connecticut labor, Connecticut nursing education, New England railroad, Connecticut business records, Connecticut's ethnic communities, Connecticut's flora, fauna and environment, Connecticut politics, the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students, etc.]. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Administrative Records.; Civil actions.; Financial Records.
- Series 1: An Inventory, 1976-2000; 39.65 Linear feet
  - Administrative records, correspondence, legal documents, financial records, 1981, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, numbered 0001-0493 (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    International Rescue Committe, New Jersey Office, State of New Jersey Legal Immigration and Employment for Internationals into the United States, Peru, Mozambique, *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles),
    Administrative Records.; International organization.; Legal Records.
  - Administrative records, correspondence, legal documents, notes, 1976, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 0502-0999 (Box 2)
    International Rescue Committe, State of New Jersey, Immigrants From Ecuador, Puerto Rico, Peru, World Education Services, Inc., *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, notes, 1986, 1987, 1990; 0.5 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 1001-1149 (Box 3)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration from Mexico, Santo Domingo, Colombia, *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, notes, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989; 1.5 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 1150-1512 (Box 4)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration from Puerto Rico, Ecuador, Dominican Republic, *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, notes, financial records, 1988, 1989, 1995; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 1513-1945 (Box 5)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services, Immigration and Employment from Puerto Rico, Peru, Dominican Republic, Santo Domingo, Argentina, Guatemala, Ecuador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (facsimiles),
    Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; International organization.; Legal Records.
  - Administrative records, correspondence, notes, legal documents, financial records, 1989, 1991, 1992; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 1949-2500 (Box 6)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Ecuador, Nicaragua, Colombia; *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, notes, 1989, 1990, 1992, 1994, 1995, 1996; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 2501-2730 (Box 7)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from USSR, Mexico, Colombia, Santo Domingo, Panama, Peru; Career Center, Inc.; *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles)
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, postcards, notes, clippings, 1990, 1992, 1996; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 2731-3000 (Box 8)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Santo Domingo, Ethiopia, Dominican Republic, Ecuador, Puerto Rico, El Salvador; *Social Security Cards and Numbers (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, notes, correspondence, legal documents, 1990, 1991, 1995, 1996; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 3001-3239 (Box 9)
    International Rescue Committe, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Dominican Republic, Nicaragua, Santo Domingo, Ecuador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards,
  - Administrative records, notes, legal documents, financial records, 1991; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 3242-3470 (Box 10)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, World Education Service, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services, Immigration and Employment from Puerto Rico, Santo Domingo, Ecuador, Peru, El Salvador, Colombia; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (facsimiles)
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, photographs (facsimiles), 1991, 1992, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 3472-3775 (Box 11)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Colombia, Peru, Turkey; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, notes, 1993, 1994, 1996; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 3776-4150 (Box 12)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from El Salvador, Santo Domingo, Ecuador, Honduras, Colombia; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, notes, financial records, legal documents, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1999; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 4152-4432 (Box 13)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from El Salvador, Dominican Republic, Nicaragua, Ecuador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, notes, 1995, 1996; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 4433-4755 (Box 14)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Union City, New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Colombia, Ecuador, Santo Domingo; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, notes, legal documents, 1990, 1992, 1996, 1997; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 4756-5160 (Box 15)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Colombia, Ecuador, El Salvador, Peru; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, notes, legal documents, 1997, 1998, 1999; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 5163-5543 (Box 16)
    International Rescue Committe, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from Santo Domingo, Puerto Rico, Ecuador, Bogota, Venezuela; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, notes, 1999; 0.5 Linear feet Folders, Numbered 5546-5718 (Box 17)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services, Immigration and Employment from Colombia, Jordan, Dominican Republic, Mexico, El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, transcripts (translations), 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized A-B (Box 18)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration from El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, 1991, 1992, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized B-D (Box 19)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Newark, New Jersey, United States Department of Justice Immigration and Naturalization Service, Immigration and Employment from El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, correspondence, photographs (facsimiles), 1991, 1992, 1995, 1996, 2000; 0.5 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized B-H (Box 20)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Newark, New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, notes, correspondence, 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized D-J (Box 21)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration from El Salvador, Newark, New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service; *Social Security Numbers and Cards,
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, postcards, notes, correspondence, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized G-L (Box 22)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Immigration from El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, notes, correspondence, 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized H-M (Box 23)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, notes, 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized M-P (Box 24)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Newark, New Jersey; *Social Security Numbers and Cards,
  - Administrative records, correspondence, legal documents, notes, financial records, 1991, 1992; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized P-R (Box 25)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Newark, New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services, Immigration from El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, correspondence, transcripts, 1991, 1992, 1993; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized S-V (Box 26)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Newark, New Jersey, Immigration and Employment from El Salvador; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, correspondence, notes, 1991, 1992, 1993; 0.5 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized V-Z (Box 27)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Newark, New Jersey, Records Regarding Immigration and Employment from El Salvador; United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services; *Social Security Cards and Numbers (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, correspondence, legal documents, 1980, 1981, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998, 1999; 1.3 Linear feet Folders (Box 28)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Union City, New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Immigration of Alien Relatives from Nicaragua, Venezuela, Colombia, Dominican Republic, El Salvador; Marriage Officiation; *Social Security Numbers and Cards,
  - Administrative records, legal documents, correspondence, transcripts, financial records, 1989, 1990, 1992, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1999.; 1.3 Linear feet Folders (Box 29)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Union City, New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services, Immigration and Employment of Alien Relatives from Colombia, El Salvador, Honduras, Ecuador; Divorce and Marriage Records; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, 1986, 1988, 1991, 1992, 1997, 1998; 1.3 Linear feet Folders (Box 30)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Immigration and Employment for Immigrants from Colombia, Cuba, Ecuador, Peru; Legal Immigration Documents; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, 1989, 1993, 1997, 1998, 1999; 0.5 Linear feet Folders (Box 31)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Legal Immigration, Employment and Residency from Cuba, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Services; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, correspondence, notes, 1991, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998, 1999; 0.5 Linear feet Folders (Box 32)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service, Immigrant Affadavits of Support and Income Tax; Immigrant Travel; Immigration from Cuba; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, legal documents, financial records, clippings, correspondence, notes, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989, 1990, 1991; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Numbered A25.409.182-A39.134.888 (Box 33)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Union City, New Jersey, Immigration from Cuba and Nicaragua, United States Department of Justice, Immigration and Naturalization Service; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, notes, legal documents, financial records, 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1991; 0.25 Linear feet Folders, Numbered A39.137.270-A39.142.909 (Box 34)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Immigration and Employment in the United States for Cuban Citizens; Immigration Forms; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),
  - Administrative records, financial records, legal documents, notes, photographs, 1980, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989; 1.3 Linear feet Folders, Alphabetized A-C (Box 35)
    International Rescue Committee, State of New Jersey, Union City, New Jersey, Cuban Immigration and Employment in the United States, Spain; *Social Security Numbers and Cards (Facsimiles),